Guide to the Album palaeographicum..., 1285-1629
Department of Special Collections
Album palaeographicum...,
1285-1629
Special Collections M0388
44 documents
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Purchased, 1977.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
33 French documents, dating from the 13th to 17th centuries, pertaining primarily to property and monetary transactions, including among other items records of sale, marriage contracts, rental contracts, expense records, and a will; also several documents issued by feudal authorities. Many of these documents are in regional dialect. 10 Spanish documents relating to property in or near Cordoba, dating from the 15th and 16th centuries. One political document from the Council of Basel, ca. 1420.
Arrangement
Chronological, by language
Please note that oversize items, marked by an asterisk in this guide, are stored in the map case, separately from the rest of the collection.
Container List
- 13th/14th Century French Documents
  - Unidentified (Box 1, Folder 1a)
  - Unidentified (Box 1, Folder 1b)
    [English hand, writing in S.W. France (Aquitania)]
  - Document, 13th/14th c. (Box 1, Folder 1c)
  - Unidentified (Box 1, Folder 2a-c)
  - Document, 14th c. (Box 1, Folder 2d)
  - Contract regarding farm land. Grosbois-en-Montagne, 1318.In Bourgogne dialect. (Box 1, Folder 3a)
  - Record of sale. Breuil-Gersoy, Basses Pyrenees, 1382.In Gascogne dialect. (Box 1, Folder 3b)
  - Marriage contract, 1367. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Record of sale, 1365. (Box 1, Folder 5a)
  - Document, 1367. (Box 1, Folder 5b)
  - Expense record of a ducal administrator, ca. 1330. (Box 1, Folder 6a)
  - Directions for the use of military funds. Clermont, France, 1390. (Box 1, Folder 6b)
  - Military order issued by Charles VI of France, 1395. (Box 1, Folder 6c)
- 15th Century French Documents
  - Rental contract of a textile merchant in Metz, Jehan Theuron, ca. 1420. (Box 1, Folder 6d)
  - Unidentified (Box 1, Folder 7a-c)
  - Document, 1465. (Box 1, Folder 7d)
  - Report on the revenues of forest land. Longchamps, Andelys, 1409. (Box 1, Folder 8 *)
  - Letter of vassalage. A. de Sales, 1410.In French dialect. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Document. St. Victor, 1452. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Rental contract. Villarceau, 1482. (Box 1, Folder 11a)
- 16th and 17th Century French Documents
  - Record of sale, 1504. (Box 1, Folder 11b)
  - Unidentified (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Will. Provence, 1546.In Provencal dialect. (Box 1, Folder 13 *)
  - Marriage contract. Azomar, 1565.In Languedoc dialect. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Document. Gorre, near Metz, 1575. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Document. St. Jean, Alsace, 1597. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Legal document relating to Charles II, Duke of Lorraine. 1598. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letter of vassalage of Jean Fourneau. 19 April 1600. (Box 1, Folder 18 *)
  - Document regarding an inheritance. Metz, 1627. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Spanish documents, relating to property in or near Cordoba
  - Record of sale. 1400. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Marriage contract. Villamediana, 1402. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Record of the sale of a house. Berlanga, 1414. (Box 1, Folder 22 *)
  - Contract regarding a house, concluded between F. and G. Ruik from Villamediana, 1420. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Contract about the division of property (pre-nuptial agreement?), 1425. (Box 1, Folder 24)